My guest today has seen healthc care
from three places. Most people never get
to stand in the exam room, the Pentagon,
and the federal policy table.
What you see or what you get from
ChatgBT CLA or any of these other large
language models, LLMs, is not the
definitive answer. It may not be
accurate. They don't have the context.
They don't know you. You may not give
all the right information. When you sit
with your doctor and you come with that
information, it's the start of the
conversation. It's not the I found on
chat GPT only 12% of people are fully
health [music] literate. Well, let that
sink in for a second. We don't know
where that information is going. [music]
It's has your identifiers. A physician
has the relationship with the patient.
If you're using AI and it tells you
something or it [music] does something
autonomously for the patient, you are
still that practice, that physician is
still responsible. Do not upload your
medical record in total [music]
up into a general LLM. Just don't do it.
Welcome back to the Signal Room. I'm Chris
Hutchins. My guest today has seen
healthc care from three places most
people never get to stand in at once.
the exam room, the Pentagon, and the
federal policy table. Dr. Terry Adirim,
welcome to the Sigma Room. I'm very
excited to have you on this morning.
It's just been an extraordinary few
days, and I really enjoyed our
conversation last week and am very happy
to let some folks in on some of the
amazing work that you're doing. Uh you
you spent more than 25 years as a pediat
pediatric emergency physician. You've
led health IT overhauls at the VA. He
served as acting assistant secretary of
defense for health affairs. This is just
amazing. Before we get into too much,
I'd like to hear a little bit about your
your personal story and a bit about your
why. I know that people don't just
stumble into a kind of career that
you've had, not only as a physician, but
involved in so many different aspects of
of policym and education and and
writing. Uh definitely want to make sure
we take take a chance to take a minute
to show to really get into your new
book. I'm very excited to hear about
this, but if you could just just start
us off with a little bit of background
and what makes you tick.
Yeah. Well, thank you very much and
thank you very much, Chris, for inviting
me on uh for uh this discussion. So,
what makes me tick? I've always wanted
to be a physician. I've always wanted to
be a doctor. I've always been curious
about health and health care. And most
especially like all my colleagues, we
very much wanted to help people. And as
I was going through the process of
becoming a physician through education
and my years of training, I realized
that I could make a difference by
treating patients one onone or I could
treat larger populations by moving into
academia and then into the federal
policy sphere. So that has been my
career trajectory. I've been very
fortunate to work with a good number of
great colleagues across the spectrum
from clinical care, academia, and
federal, I would say, uh, health
agencies that I've worked in. So,
amazing. So, I want to kind of get into
some of the the interesting stuff for
for folks because right now when we're
almost every conversation that comes up
about AI, there's a there's some policy
and uh regulatory kind of aspects that
seem to be coming up, governance a bit
too. I mean, you've sat where some of
these big decisions actually get made
like in the VA, the Department of
Defense, federal health policy. Where's
the widest gap right now from your
perspective between what leadership
believes is happening with AI and and
the clinical encounter and what's
actually true out on the floor?
Sure. Uh thanks for that question. I
think right now there's a tension
between how much regulation, how much uh
policym to ensure that AI used in health
care is safe with innovation. There is
that tension and prior to this current
administration
there was an appetite for coming up with
frameworks on ethics and regulation and
governance. But when this new
administration uh came in, they wanted
to unleash AI and in to ensure that
innovators can innovate. I think it has
to be somewhere in between. I think in a
current environment, we're not quite
getting it right because I think the
health care field uh health care
community as well as patients need that
guidance. Um and it's just not happening
really right now. And hopefully because
we're in this transitional period, we'll
get to a place where we strike that
right balance because you don't want to
hinder innovation.
But in health care, it's very different
than other sectors in that we need to
make sure that we protect patients. So
that's where we are right now on a
national scale.
Can we I want to double click on that
just for a minute. if if I could could
you speak about uh some of the specific
things that that you know people should
be aware of uh you know from your your
perspectives like one of the reasons I
love having this this platform is for
when for someone like you who comes on
you you can actually send some really uh
clear messages out there so that people
that may not be paying attention have
some idea what they should be doing and
how to lean in and maybe hope push push
the influence uh in the in the right
direction. Well, I think there's uh kind
of could look at it in two ways. There
is what individuals need to do and then
there is actually three. There's what we
need to be doing nationally with regard
to the federal environment. Um there is
stuff being done on the state level and
then there's what the industry should be
looking out for. I think there with
technology in of itself is not ethical
or unethical but how we use it brings up
the issues of ethics. I think privacy in
health care is huge and I think there
are a number of things that that for
example an individual can do to protect
their privacy when AI and AI tools are
being used like one of them being don't
upload your entire medical record into
chat GBT. uh with regard to you know the
federal sphere I really think they need
to update a lot of the regulations and
policies around patient privacy that
brings in AI some of them these policies
and regulations didn't even think about
AI it came before you know AI became a
thing in healthcare so I think we that
that could be attended to and then
lastly I think the industry too needs to
respect um health care and needs to
understand it differently than some of
the other sectors. So let me give you an
example. When you people who uh you know
for lack of better term tech bros they
like to move fast and break things in
health care the culture is very much
about do no harm don't hurt patients. So
there could be conflicts between those
two ethos which um I think it's
important to reconcile and I think um
health tech companies have a
responsibility
to understand the do no harm and to
respect that and understand that those
of us who want to use these tools very
much are looking forward to all these
innovations want to make sure that
there's that respect and I think that
tension will be there for a while
longer, but I think that something that
could be paid attention to.
That's amazing. And I I really
appreciate you bringing some clarity to
to this stuff because it's just such a
unbelievably fastm moving transformation
that's going on. To your point, the
innovations definitely outpacing uh the
responsible and ethical use and a lot of
the policy and guardrail things that
really need to be put in place to
protect patients. Well, like like you
said, I mean, first do no harp. We we
didn't all go to medical school and take
that oath, but we need to support that
oath and make sure that we're backing it
up by what we deliver. No question about
that. We have a lot of opportunities to
do better. This kind of nicely steps
over into the topic of your book, which
I'm really excited to hear about, but
the prepared patient. Talk to me about
that. What does that phrase mean to you?
and and you know how did you how did you
come up with this particular title based
on all your experiences in what's
happening now and I suspect it's not
about an AI but an unveiling type of
thing and trying to prepare patients for
that but I mean I'll leave it there and
just I just want to hear all about it.
Yeah. No, thank you. Um it's a broader
uh topic and and the book is called the
prepared patient your guide to surviving
the health care system. And I was
inspired by two things. One was the
statistic that only 12% of people are
fully health literate. Now, let that
sink in for a second. That is a really
astounding statistic. And what does that
mean? That means that if you don't know
fully about your health coverage, what
to expect, and how to navigate the
system, that could have impacts on your
health outcomes and on your finances.
So, that's number one. But what really
inspired me was early in my career, I
took care of a lot of families with
children who have special health care
needs, medically complex children. And
what impressed me about them is that
they came to the emergency department,
which is where I spent uh my clinical
part of my career. They always came with
these white binders that had all of
their information. And as a physician
who didn't necessarily know this
patient, fully appreciated having all
their medications with their dosages,
their medical diagnosis, who their
specialists were, and just all the
information um that I needed to care for
that child. Now, we of course scroll
ahead 25 years later. We don't
necessarily have a white binder, though
you can put it in paper. You could do it
electronically.
But um the point I'm trying to make is
that they wanted the best outcomes for
their children. So they were fully
prepared. So that's the inspiration for
this book. Our health system, no matter
how smart you are, no matter how
educated you are, could be challenging
to navigate and difficult to understand.
That challenge is this is strangely
enough. I actually had had someone on
probably six or eight weeks ago. I'm not
really sure timing wise, but she she she
had a a child who had really really rare
disease and she talked about this exact
thing that you just mentioned where
she's constantly having to keep
everything updated and you know how
difficult it is that every time you got
you want to go see a new specialist,
it's Groundhog Day and I mean from your
perspective um isn't are there some
things that we should be challenging our
our technology companies to do because I
that's a pretty big part of what to care
just seems like that's a a a risk
because we not we might not even have it
for for the physician when they need
they were going to treat the patient,
right? And 25 years ago, I would have
kind of hoped that we would have been
further along, you know, in 2026. Um,
but there are several factors that have
been challenges to make it more of a
smooth, super well-connected health care
system. I mean, even just a few years
back, I was working in the emergency
department and I got a a a patient, a
young patient and family was transferred
from another hospital. So, as I'm asking
the father questions, he's like, "Yeah,
we just we just answered all these
questions and we had all these tests
done. Isn't it in your" and he pointed
to the electronic health record, right?
And I said, "You know, I'm really sorry,
but you came from a different health
care system." Right? So within the same
health care system, if you're taken care
of at Kaiser or Mayo or Cleveland
Clinic, like sure, your records would be
in there and you go see a subsp
specialist who's affiliated with that
system, that information would be there.
So that would be step one. But that's
not how things operate. Just like your
guest on, you know, several weeks ago,
she may need to see different
specialists in different health care
systems. And one of the fixes has not
really been a a full fix has been these
health information exchanges. But even
that those are kind of clunky. You have
to pull the information doesn't
automatically populate and you know
people have to agree to be a part of
that. So we still have a very disjointed
fragmented
health care system which makes it so
challenging especially for the over 50%
of people in this country who have
chronic medical conditions and for that
child who's got multiple conditions.
They're seeing multiple specialists. are
getting multiple tests unfortunately and
it's not fair and it's not necessarily
right but the responsibility then
becomes on the patient or that patient's
family. So that's what I was trying to
do with this book is to help people get
themselves organized, get themselves
prepared, figure out what types of
information that you need, for example,
to bring to your appointment, what types
of information you need with regard to
your healthc care coverage. Now that
it's all not all doom and gloom, right?
AI is helping to smooth some of these
friction points for patients. So, for
example, you can collect all this
information electronically, right? You
can do that. Um, and there are companies
that are working on doing this for
people who've got complex medical needs.
There's also within the exam room things
that could help the physician, right? So
for example if a patient's medical
record is within that system the in a
lot of places the physician could get a
summary that's you know ex that is
created by AI right so now there's a
number of institutions I would I don't
think it's most but there's a lot of
institutions and doctor's offices that
are using something called AI ambient
scribes meaning that the physician isn't
sitting there typing way while they're
talking to you. A voice activated system
turns on while while the patient and
physician are talking and takes notes,
organizes the notes and the physician
can ask for a summary of that. You could
even do a patient summary and give that
to the patient about their visit. So
there are these things that are not
solving the problem, but they're really
reducing those friction points that you
brought up uh for people who have to see
multiple specialists.
Yeah, I I think um to people out there
who can actually develop and design
stuff, we're still talking about the
same lack of interoperability here.
And I don't know how many times I've
heard this over a decade now. And we're
still we still haven't solved for it.
And there there's just no good reasons
for it.
It's been longer than a decade.
Yeah,
you're being nice by saying a decade.
It's, you know, it's been fraught and
difficult because, you know, there's a
number of laws around privacy. The way
that EHRs were established, companies
establish their electronic health
records and they're proprietary. So,
they don't want to share and connect.
And so that took a long time to improve
that problem and then also develop
health information exchanges. They're
not perfect solutions, but you know,
it's it's a lot of regulatory issues and
proprietary issues and how electronic
health records were established that
have made it not easy for physicians or
patients.
Right. Well, I mean that unfortunately
it was it was designed to do more
accurate billing instead of actually
supporting clinical workflow and that's
and quite honestly it hasn't done a
great job with either. That's the part
that's unfortunate.
Yeah, we have such a complex health
system. But what the the the future is
going to hold and where I think um we're
going to see improvements is that the
electronic health record is not going to
go away. It's going to be that system of
record. But hopefully what we're going
to see are innovators, and we're
starting to see this, build and design
products that are layered above the EHR,
can extract stuff from the EHR, but then
operate kind of above it. So that from
the very start, let's say it's a primary
care practice, you have AI tools that
help with appointments. There'll be chat
box patients don't have to wait and they
could do all that kind of upfront work
automatically all the way to ambient AI
scribes in the exam room um to patient
discharge instructions. You already have
electronic prescribing but you know
really amplify that or I'd say augment
that. There's other tools on the back
end too that also help patients with
referrals and so on. And there's the
companies there are companies that are
doing what's called RCM, but that
billing kind of work. So, one day, I
predict we're not even going to need to
necessarily touch that electronic health
record. Maybe just the people within the
companies and big health systems might
need to touch it, but hopefully we'll
get to a place where we have systems in
place that make it with less friction
for patients and physicians.
That should be the objective right
there. I mean I one where one of the
litmus tests that I've I like to talk
about is first and foremost before we
talk about any other aspect I just want
to know is it going to give time back to
the people who need that whether it's
you know the the physician the nurse the
MA u most importantly you know the the
time for that encounter between a
physician and their patient that's got
to be the bar that we're shooting for I
just think that we do a lot of stuff
because we think it's cool technology
Unfortunately, that's happened a lot
latin healthcare and that's that's just
not been helpful. It's been disruptive
from everyone I've talked to, including
yourself. There's there's definitely
some some areas that have been, you
know, just glaring and then then they
haven't been touched. I mean,
interoperability is not a small thing.
And honestly, I don't think it's the
most complicated thing in the world, but
there's got to be some
it is to the regulations to to force
that to finally happen.
Yeah, it's it's more complicated than
you'd imagine. But to your point, I
think AI is going to be a help. I think
on balance, it's a positive thing and I
think the future um things will be
better. It will not solve the problems
of our health care system because our
health care system is built on policies,
regulations, laws, and so on that make
it this multi-layer, and now I'm going
to use a big SAT word, accreted, you
know, everything is just all kind of
glombmed together. hard to extricate all
the different pieces. So AI is not
really going to fix that. We're gonna
have to have the political will to want
to make the changes that we need in
order to unfragment, unopy, I don't
know, whatever terms you want to use of
our health care system. But I really
believe that technology
can improve the experience for both the
you know clinicians and for um patients.
And I I I I agree with you there. Let's
talk a little bit about what you the
dynamics there that are actually
changing now where uh a patient may show
up already having worked through their
own differential before they even sat
down. What are you seeing in in
practice? I in this case I'm assuming
it's you know the the parents who would
be coming in having done their own AI re
we'll call it research but
yeah well you know you pediatrics u
pediatric emergency medicine children
who are medically complex and with
special health care needs their parents
know their condition and if it's a rare
condition they know more than you do
because in the emergency department
you're a bit of a generalist so they've
done their research and I've, you know,
started practice when people were
beginning to go on the internet and
check, you know, Google their conditions
and stuff. So, it's been around for a
while. What I would say is different.
There's several differences. One of the
differences is that back then
people would Google a lot of it was
wrong. People didn't know how to sort
through that kind of stuff. And there
was a lot of resistance by the medical
community, right? And but I think scroll
ahead to now. I think AI could actually
be like a patient co-pilot or you know
really help patients and I think
physicians
you know uh many of them not all of them
are less resistant see it as an
opportunity right because I I really
like when my patients know know things
you know I I want them to be engaged in
their um health and their health care
but I think there's a responsibility on
the patients too right what you
or what you get from chat GBT cla or any
of these other um large language models
LLMs um may is not the definitive
answer. It may not be accurate. They
don't have the context. They don't know
you. You may not give it all the right
information. When you sit with your
doctor and you come with that
information, it's the start of the
conversation. It's not the I found on
chat GPT that I have, you know, I must
have lung cancer, right? No, that's not
that's not how that should work. It
should be the beginning of that
conversation and it takes it to a
different level, right? As a physician,
you're not starting from scratch. You're
like, "Oh, well, so tell me a little bit
about what you found." Well, here, let
me tell you why that's not quite right.
I did this test and it showed this. It
showed that. So I think it could be a
good thing as long as both physicians
kind of know you know how to work with
it and patients also know how to work
with it. So I think overall equals the
playing field a bit levels the playing
field which I think is good because in
medicine we've traditionally been a very
paternalistic
um field but I I I like the fact that it
can help empower patients and prepare
them for their care. So I see it on
balance as a good thing.
It kind of kind of gets into the, you
know, the it's the the edges of uh of
real governance. You you've written on
AI and accountability in care when AI
shapes a diagnostic recommendation or
flags of coverage denial, who actually
owns that outcome in your opinion?
Yeah. Okay. That's a complex issue. If
you're using it in your practice, you as
the clinician, the practice is
responsible for the output of that AI
because you as the clinician or provider
are the individuals or organization that
is delivering the care, right? The LLM,
the GPTs or whatever they are or the AI
are tools in your practice. So you have
to look at them as tools in your
practice. They are not delivering that
care. So it's who is responsible for the
delivery of the care. A physician has
the relationship with the patient. If
you're using AI and it tells you
something or it does something
autonomously for the patient, you are
still that practice that physician is
still responsible for the care. So
always the physician or the practice.
You also talk about the approach to to
designing AI. You know, essentially
you're I think that you're agreeing with
probably almost any any physician I've
had a chance to talk to in the last
several months. Almost everyone's
telling me the same thing. You said we
need to design AI with care providers,
not around them. Where have you watched
that step get skipped and what broke as
a result of it?
Yeah. Wow, that's a great question. I've
talked to a lot of well-meaning founders
of startups and you know not having
somebody that's either a co-founder with
you or within that leadership structure
who is a clinician and I believe it
should be a physician means that you may
identify a problem but there's a good
chance you have not found that solution
or you're not creating the solution.
solution. Physicians know how care is
delivered. We know our patients. We know
what works, right? You could be smart,
but a business degree or a com computer
or I should say software engineering
degree does not
make you an expert in healthcare.
So that's foundational right from the
start. And I have talked to founders who
identify the problem and I'm like that's
great. I know you want to solve this but
then they come up with a solution which
doesn't which probably wouldn't fit
right. The other thing too is physicians
have to use these tools right so not
having them in the loop is probably not
that probably not the wisest uh
approach. So and the reason why I think
this happens that physicians are not uh
brought in early in in some cases. I
think we may be seen because we have the
ethos of do no harm and people you know
startups have the ethos of work fast
break things. There could be some seen
as some conflict between those two. And
what I see is that people who are
inventors or innovators, I think some of
that speed in getting things done could
rub off on physicians and physicians
there do no harm either should rub off
on the innovators. So I see that as
really important that it's they work
together because at the end of the day
we do not want software engineers doing
healthcare. I don't think they want to
do healthcare. But that's at the end of
the day that's brilliant.
It's it's interesting. I I've seen it go
the other direction. I've seen some
brilliant uh clinicians who have
developed really great solutions for
things and that's always been like
beyond my ability to comprehend how
someone can
have so many different things going at
the same time and that creative things.
it it just seems to manifest itself in
really interesting technologies. I I had
a chance a number of years ago to to
work with a was a pediatric neurosurgeon
and he actually developed some software
in his garage. Uh I think he probably
used like four or five different
programming languages and every once in
a while he'd see something that inspired
him. He he'd go figure out how to use
that that language and he put it into
his tool. But I you know mind-blowing. I
think it's easier to teach physicians
how to be in innovators and business
than it is to teach you know business
people healthcare right because you know
I spent many years in school I spent
years in training um at extra training I
had at one time three board
certifications so learning that does not
happen quickly I know a lot of people
think you know they know healthcare I
think we're seeing we're in a transition
itional period where we're seeing a lot
of physicians who not only have business
degrees. I have a business degree but
also are in the innovation field
developing technologies. And it's
especially important that it's people
who've practiced, right? The nuros
surgeon that you site probably been
practicing for a good number of years
and over and over again we see the same
problems and we say we need to fix this.
Right? But there wasn't a day that went
by I was in the ER like why can't we fix
this particular thing and I would say
even early in my career I was like why
are we handwriting notes why can't we
have electronic records and and you know
I did try and create something but
didn't work out uh but we but that's you
know we want to we want to uh fix the
problems that are in healthcare so
it it is amazing I think the first
couple of months And when I launched my
my company, there were I would say it
was almost a third of the people I would
meet
that were founders. About a third of
them were were physicians. And you know,
it was that's one of the things that
motivated me to to to start this
platform to to give people a voice that
that really have something to say about
this stuff because you people aren't
inventing things because everything's
working for them in their electronic
healthare,
right?
There's there's fs
across the board. I think everybody
knows that our health system is broken
and and has problems. But the one thing
is and I don't have the statistic for
it, but I know it's true that the most
successful health startups have
physicians as founders or co-founders.
Yeah, that's that's not surprising to me
at all. It's it's a strange approach
that's I've seen it in even working in
revenue cycle systems years ago and I'm
sure I'm sure you've been around this
too. one of the a vendor that you've
you've been working with for years, they
want to do something uh unique to really
take a nice leap forward and give you
better capability. So, they come in,
they conduct a few interviews of
sometimes they'll do that as much as a
week. Uh then they go away for a while
and spring a new product on you that
doesn't even resemble the things that
you talked about when they did the
interview and they they don't understand
why you don't want to use it. That's why
you have to have the people who are
using it there and it's critically
important and I found this out when I
was at the VA. We were doing electronic
health record deployments. We did have
the end users there. But changing how
they did their work really can be
upsetting. It's disruptive. Um and so
having the clinicians there could help
smooth that out. They can help with
product design. They can help with how
it's being used. And that's critically
important because if the end user won't
use it or they used workarounds then
your efforts have gone to waste.
Let's talk about a couple of different
things. No,
one of the things that you've mentioned
to me that previously was um some of the
policies that are in place now that
rules for maintaining board
certification forbidding use of AI to
answer exam questions being one of
those. Yeah. In real practice, you know,
clinicians, you know, they consult
outside evidence constantly. What does
that tell us when the way we test
doctors is out of step with the way they
actually practice?
Yeah. Well, first I have to say I am
only aware of my board certification,
the American Board of Pediatrics. They
say you can't use AI to answer the
questions. But I think, you know, just
like other parts of of health and health
care, the whole environment, they're
going to have to catch up. And you know
the old way of doing things uh was to
memorize right we you learn a boatload
of stuff during medical school and
you're supposed to um memorize all of
these things and then you know memorize
the crab cycle and then you take board
exams and we take several exams. We
take, you know, uh, boards, you know,
part one, two, three, and then we take
our specialty boards and our subsp
specialty boards. And it was the
oldfashioned way was memorizing a lot of
facts and material, but that doesn't
align with how we practice medicine,
right? We've had these clinical decision
support tools at our fingertips for a
while now. uh things like up todate
algorithms from our professional
societies and now AI with uh tools like
open evidence and there's others as well
that I've used. You know when you're
practicing you don't have to rely on a
memorization necessarily to extract that
information. So, the testing for keeping
up your board certification needs to
kind of come up come up and be a more
aligned with how we really practice
medicine. Not that I don't think
memorization's important. I still think
in in medical school it's important to
memorize a lot of these facts so that
you have them and and have a very good
understanding.
But when it comes to later in your
career after you've practiced, you know,
asking to regurgitate facts is probably
not the best way uh to test physicians.
So, we need to think about ways that we
can we can use AI to update how we
assess uh physician uh capabilities.
I'm curious about the the way medical
the medical schools run now. Do you have
concerns um that they start to get
people using this AI early on in in
their training? Uh what I'm kind of
getting at there is there's a lot of
stuff that you go through. I mean, I
know I don't know the half of it, but
you go through all the all the the class
time, all the you know, all the uh
rotations with when you're doing a
residency, all those types of things. I
I wonder if there's a a [snorts] need to
make sure that we're not I don't want to
call say dumbing it down, but I mean I
think there's a risk maybe for for
inhibiting the development, the
reasoning and the judgment that has to
be be ingrained in someone when they're
being taught how to how to be a
physician.
Yeah. No, and I think medical educators
are aware of that. Um, and it is, you
know, a concern that those critical
thinking skills and, you know, I'm
hopeful that it'll it may change how we
operate and work, but that we would
still need those critical thinking
skills. Um, and we just need to figure
out how we uh promote that and cult
cultivate that, but it'll be in
different ways because we can't say no
to AI when it's being used already
pretty extensively. So, I think it's
going to be up to medical educators to
kind of think about how we educate for
the future, right? And I think they're
starting to do that. I want to get into
another area. And this one's interesting
for me because I because you're you're
um you're also heavily involved in in in
public policy and you obviously you've
worked in in government as well. The
concept of informed consent. Uh there's
a lot of conversations that are
happening especially now because there's
been some some lawsuits because of the
how how things have been implemented
with ambient listening. uh how do you
think about that and and what is it that
we need to be be doing in order to help
a patient to understand what it is
they're consenting to because I don't
think historically we've done a good job
of even explaining the the informed
consent even in the way that it was was
prior to you know this this whole
ambient listening thing.
Yeah. Um I think there's been people
who've criticized um informed consent,
but informed consent is critically
important, right? Because if you know
you're of sound mind, you're an adult,
you should be making decisions about
your care, right?
Right.
So there's different levels of consent.
There's consent somebody just to walk in
the emergency department that you
consent to somebody delivering your
care. Right. So,
um, I don't need extra consent for
drawing blood, getting X-rays, doing a
physical exam.
But if you're doing something more
invasive, then you need an additional
consent. And that always involves laying
out what it is that you're going to do,
emphasizing that this is a choice. You
don't have to do it, but if you don't,
here's what's going to happen. and the
pros and cons of that particular whether
it's surgery whether it's a procedure
when it comes to ambient AI scribing the
central issue is is privacy right and
being informed means that the patient
understands where that recording is
going where it's stored and what are the
privacy safeguards uh how long it is
stored uh whether or not they have a
choice to use AI scribe or not. So,
those are some of the things that
patients need to look out for, but
physicians need to really be um
intentional. When a patient walks into
their room, they need to say, "I use
something called an ambient AI scribe.
It is a recording. We keep it only for a
month. It is you we follow all the laws
with HIPPA and so on. do are you okay
with me using this ambient AI scribe?
Right.
Um that's informed. Right. That took a
couple that took a minute. Right. But I
really believe that if you're going to
use something like that where privacy
can become a concern, then I think you
know consent should be had. Now not
everybody believes that way. I've been
in rooms where people have said, "Oh, I
wouldn't ask for consent." There was a a
conference I went to where they were
talking about a chatbot that does
appointments and all that pre-appoint
work. And I asked, "Well, do you get
consent? Um, do you think you have to
get consent?" And half the room said,
"No." And I'm like, "Well, yes.
[laughter]
I mean, yes, you need to tell, you know,
you need to at least say at the start,
this is a chatbot and I'm going to be
doing, you know, making your
appointment." That could be enough,
right? Because it's not such a big deal,
right? But with health care, there are
special regulations and policies around
privacy and we need to respect that.
Yeah, absolutely right. I think one of
the challenges that I've been concerned
about is how do we make it really easy
and consumable so that you know as a
physician you you don't have to go get
another degree to be able to explain AI.
I mean, I don't I don't mean to
be flip about. I'm just I just think
it's something that we have to think
about as we're as we're scaling.
And it's going to get there. It's going
to get there because we use tools all
the time that I couldn't tell you how it
works, but we use it. You just need to
get to that level of trust. But right
now, we're in this transitional period,
right, where more asking more permission
and consent is probably the better
practice right now.
Right.
We've talked about a few of the
challenges in and and some of the
interesting benefits, but one thing that
um I started to see this a few years ago
when I was was in New York um that there
was this big push to make sure that
we're we're giving people their test
results as quickly as we possibly can.
The pace now that we can do these
things, AI is kind of speeding that up
even further. What are your thoughts
around that? I I think one of the things
that was was concerning was getting a
diagnosis on a Friday that's coming out
of a lab result going into the weekend
and that then the results not something
that someone's going to be comfortable
with. Uh talk a little bit about that
from your perspective and what we should
be thinking about in trying to make sure
that we're syncing up uh the the speed
with uh the the actual preparation
that's required to be responsible with
it.
Yeah. Yeah. Sometimes when laws are
passed and this law was passed in the
cures act, best intentions, but then the
unintended consequences are not
necessarily thought about. Right? So you
identified a scenario where it would not
be ideal that somebody gets their test
results on a Friday night, right? I
think overall it's a good thing because
people should have access to their test
results. uh the responsibility is on the
physician who ordered the test to make
sure that the patient gets the test, but
there may be a different way we're going
to have to practice, right? So, let's
say um a patient gets a test result, you
know, they're going to chat GPT or one
of those things to find out, you know,
what it means, right? Well, how about a
physician? If I'm doing a test and I
said, "Look, I'm going to be doing a
complete blood count. I'm anticipating
you might have a low hemoglobin. That's
a red red cell. If it's low, it may mean
you have anemia. It may not it, you
know, I'm not thinking that you have
cancer or this or that. So, you may need
to do a little bit of prep preparation
when you're doing the tests so that when
the result comes back, and that was too
simple. That's a routine test. But let's
say you're doing a um a biopsy, right?
and you're worried that it's cancer, you
should I think what best practice would
be is to say, I'm doing this test
because I'm concerned that you will have
an abnormality like a you know a cancer
or mass and discuss it pre preemptively
so that when the patient does access
that information it's not so much of a a
surprise and in that preamble say but we
have we have treatments for that so I'm
happy to talk to you about it if you get
that test result. So, we may need to
change a little bit that you know how we
practice, you know, adjust a little bit
that workflow. But, um I think in
general it was a good thing to do. I
think it would have been good to think
about it about what the repercussions
and what the consequences
uh were going to be beforehand. I think
that law was passed like in 2018. So,
hopefully
yeah,
practices have worked on that. But,
yeah.
interesting that that it comes full
circle um back to where we started your
book, the prepared patient. It it's I
love how you just describe that that
whole scenario because that's really uh
what what's needed when you to res when
you've got these kind of requirements uh
the you got to think through this how do
you prepare the patient. So I want to
make sure we leave people with something
that they can they can use here. So if
you're talking to a patient right now
who wants to bring AI into their own
care, what's the one thing that they
should always do and one thing they
should never do?
All right, let's start with never do. I
advise everybody do not upload your
medical record in total up into a
general LLM. Just don't do it, right? Uh
it's we don't know where that
information is going. It's has your
identifiers like don't do that. That
would be one of the things. I could
think of others. I would also just
because this is going to get to what you
should do. I would not take everything
that is said. If you put your
information, you'd say, "Oh, I have a
mole on my arm and it comes back with
what it could be and it gives you this
long list." Use that as a start of your
conversation. Don't automatically assume
it's melanoma, right? It's not cancer.
Bring that to your physician and say,
"You know what? I put that into chat GPT
and it gave me this differential. Let
your physician talk to you, have a
conversation about uh what it's more
likely to be based on what you know uh
her experience and what her she's
looking at and all the data in order to
come up with that diagnosis. I think
people should understand what they get
from these LLMs. There's probably a high
amount of accuracy. I think we have
studies that show that there's a highly
accurate, but I think understand that uh
general LLMs are just spewing out
information, right? Physicians are not
information spewers. We do more than
that, right? So, the LLM does not have
your context, your family history, your
physical exam, all the other pieces that
we put together as that puzzle to come
up with a diagnosis or a plan for you.
So, as I said, it needs to be the start
of the conversation, something you bring
to your appointment. um so that you
could start at a place that is ahead of
having to get you know all the basic
information you could actually have a
good conversation I think it's also a
good tool to ask it what kind of
question should I be asking at my
appointment knowing that appointments
are you know for routine appointments
could be 15 20 minutes long you don't
have a lot of time so you should
prioritize what questions you're asking
and that's what I talk about in I booked
the prepared patient about being
prepared for your appointments um would
be very helpful uh to you and getting
the most out of those appointments.
But as we as we wrap up our
conversation, uh tell tell folks where
they can get a hold of you and where
they can pre-order your book.
Yes. No, thank you. Well, my book is
available for pre-order on Amazon and
the John's Hopkins University Press,
which is the publisher. It's being
released on August 11th, so weeks away
from it actually being released, but
right now you can purchase it on Amazon.
Um, and if this is recorded, if this is
released after August 11th, then then it
it's available um on a lot of book
sellers. Um, and I could be reached um
I'm on LinkedIn under my name. um on
TerryMD
um on X um uh Instagram and I have a
website called
www.thepreparedpatient.com
uh which has all the information about
where you could get the book and so on.
Fantastic. And for for listeners uh
you'll find all all this information
that Dr. Terry just shared and it'll be
in the show notes. uh we'll make sure
you know how to find her and please make
sure that you you take a take a snapshot
of the of the screen when you see the
the pre-order link and you you
definitely want to get this book. I'
I've learned a lot from you this morning
and I I really do appreciate you coming
on this show.
Thank you. Thank you so much for having
this conversation with me. I truly
appreciate it.
Dr. is Terry Adirim, physician, former
federal health leader and author of the
prepared patient out this August from
John's Hopkins University Press. The
thread I am taking with me today is the
patient already has a co-pilot. The real
question is whether the system is
prepared to go meet them. Go pre-order
the book. And Terry, thank you so much
for joining me today. And for my
audience, I'll see you next time on the
Signal Room. That's it for this episode
of the Signal Room. If today's
conversation sparked something in you,
an idea, a challenge, or a perspective
worth amplifying, I'd love to hear from
you. Message me on LinkedIn or visit
cigarroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming